Finding Aid for the Ralph J. Bunche papers LSC.2051
UCLA Library Special Collections
Ralph J. Bunche papers
1927-1971
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.2051
221 linear feet (443 boxes, 7 cartons, and 47 oversize boxes)
Ralph J. Bunche (1904-1971) graduated from UCLA and Harvard University, and was a professor at Howard University (1929-1950). He joined the Permanent Secretariat of the United Nations in 1948, served as the undersecretary for special political affairs (1958-67), and then became undersecretary general in 1968. In 1950, Bunche was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize. The collection consists of correspondence, speeches, manuscripts, articles, publications, and photographs related to Ralph J. Bunche's life and career.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Conditions Governing Access
Family requested that series 21, subseries 1: Personal Correspondence between Ralph J. Bunche and Ruth H. Bunche (boxes 476-480) were closed until the deaths of both Joan H. Bunche and Ralph Bunche Jr. As of April 2021, the family would like to review the materials in these boxes before lifting the restriction.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Ruth H. Bunche, 1976, 1982.
Gift of Brian Urquhart, 1995.
Gift of Joan H. Bunche, 1995.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 997095173606533
Biography
Bunche, Ralph Johnson (7 Aug. 1904-9 Dec. 1971), scholar and diplomat, was born in Detroit, Michigan, the son of Fred Bunch, a barber, and Olive Agnes Johnson. His grandmother added an "e" to the family's last name following a move to Los Angeles, California. Because his family moved frequently, Bunche attended a number of public schools before graduating first in his class from Jefferson High School in Los Angeles in 1922. He majored in political science at the University of California, Southern Branch (now University of California, Los Angeles or UCLA). He graduated summa cum laude and served as class valedictorian in 1927. He continued his studies in political science at Harvard, receiving his M.A. in 1928, then taught at Howard University in Washington, D.C., while working toward his Ph.D. at Harvard. In 1930 he married Ruth Ethel Harris; they had three children. Bunche traveled to Europe and Africa researching his dissertation and received his Ph.D. from Harvard in February 1934.
Concerned with the problems facing African Americans in the United States, Bunche published numerous articles on racial issues and the monograph A World View of Race (1936). He and his colleague John P. Davis organized a 1935 conference called "The Status of the Negro under the New Deal," at which Bunche criticized the Franklin D. Roosevelt administration and the New Deal. He was also involved in the creation of the National Negro Congress, an attempt to bring white Americans and African Americans of different social and economic backgrounds together to discuss race matters. In the final years of the decade Bunche contributed research and reports to a Carnegie study on American race relations headed by sociologist Gunnar Myrdal. The resulting work, An American Dilemma: The Negro Problem and Modern Democracy, published in 1944, was a landmark study of racial conflicts in the United States.
The rise of totalitarianism in Europe and the outbreak of war in 1939 worried Bunche, who feared that a Nazi victory in Europe would spur the growth of fascism in the United States, with disastrous consequences for African Americans. In 1941 he entered public service, accepting a position as a senior analyst in the Office of the Coordinator of Information (later the Office of Strategic Services). As head of the Africa Section, Bunche urged his superiors to approach the problem of postwar decolonization of European holdings in Africa. His proposal was rejected, and he transferred to the Department of State in 1944.
Bunche served as an adviser to the American delegations at the conferences in Dumbarton Oaks and San Francisco concerning the creation of the United Nations (UN). Recognized for his contributions on colonial and trusteeship policies, he was appointed a member of the U.S. delegation to the 1945 meeting of the Preparatory Commission of the UN and the first session of the UN General Assembly in 1946. In April 1946 Bunche took a temporary position on the United Nations Secretariat as director of the trusteeship position. The temporary position became permanent, and he served on the UN Secretariat for the remainder of his life.
In 1947 Bunche was appointed to the United Nations Special Committee on Palestine. He drafted both the majority report, which recommended a partition of the territory between Palestinians and Jews, and the minority report, which called for the creation of a federal state. The UN General Assembly accepted the partition plan, and Bunche was named the principal secretary for a commission designed to oversee its implementation. With the outbreak of war in 1948, Bunche was appointed as an assistant to the UN mediator, Count Folke Bernadotte. Following Bernadotte's assassination in September of that year, Bunche became the acting mediator. He successfully negotiated armistice agreements between Israel and several Arab states and was awarded the 1950 Nobel Peace Prize for his efforts.
Bunche's commitment to the United Nations did not prevent him from speaking out against racial discrimination in the United States. In 1949 he turned down a position as assistant secretary of state, noting that he did not want to experience the blatant discrimination against African Americans that existed in the nation's capital.
Bunche was appointed an undersecretary-general for special political affairs in 1954. With the outbreak of the Suez crisis in 1956, he was again called upon to use his diplomatic skills in a Middle Eastern conflict, and he organized the UN Emergency Force that was responsible for peacekeeping activities in the region. His Middle East experience prepared him for the difficulties he faced in 1960, when he organized and commanded both the military and civilian branches of the UN peacekeeping force sent to the Congo. He again directed a peacekeeping force when conflicts erupted on the island of Cyprus in 1964.
Bunche continued to press for the civil rights of African Americans. Though he still hoped for a society free from racial division, the civil rights conflicts of the late 1960s troubled him greatly. He participated in the 1965 march from Selma to Montgomery with Martin Luther King, Jr. However, Bunche found himself under attack from leaders, such as Stokely Carmichael and Malcolm X, who argued that he had served white society and abandoned his African heritage. In turn, Bunche denounced the separatist agenda of the Black Power movement. Health problems, many related to his diabetes, slowed him in the final years of his life. He died in New York City.
During his lifetime Bunche garnered international recognition and numerous rewards for his United Nations service, including the U.S. Medal of Freedom in 1963. Though his position earned him the derision of many civil rights leaders in the 1960s, he was dedicated to the cause of African-American civil rights throughout his career. By using his diplomatic skills in the service of the United Nations, he promoted the cause of peace in a world that sorely needed men of dedication and ability in this area.
Thomas Clarkin. "Bunche, Ralph Johnson"; http://www.anb.org/articles/07/07-00424.html; American National Biography Online Feb. 2000.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of correspondence, speeches, manuscripts, articles, publications, photographs, and awards related to the life and career of Ralph J. Bunche. Includes materials related to his teaching and research, his affiliations with various service organizations, educational institutions and international conferences.
The collection includes Bunche's graduate research materials on Africa (photographs and field notes); research and reports from his participation in the Carnegie-Myrdal study on race in the America; U.S. Office of Strategic Services (OSS) reports; Institute of Pacific Relations (IPR) documents; materials related to Bunche's involvement with the United Nations (UN), including Trusteeship records, and materials dealing with his appointment as undersecretary of the UN in 1954; and material related to Bunche's receipt of the Nobel Peace Prize in 1950.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
21.1 Personal Correspondence: CLOSED.
21.2 Ralph Bunche
21.3 Ruth Bunche
21.4 Bunche Family
21.5 Ralph Bunche memorials and tributes
Related Material
Interview of Charles H. Matthews, Remembering Ralph Bunche. UCLA Library Special Collections, Center for Oral History Research interview, 1973. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Grace M. Thomas Collection about Ralph Bunche (Collection 2079). Available at the UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library.
Brian Urquhart Collection of Material about Ralph Bunche (Collection 364). Available at the UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library.
Ralph J. Bunche Papers, Collection Sc MG 290. Available at The New York Public Library Manuscripts, Archives and Rare Books Division Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture.
UN Archives in New York City: http://archives-trim.un.org/
Online Items Available
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online:
UCLA Digital Library: Ralph J. Bunche Papers (93 items).
Calisphere: Ralph J. Bunche Papers (97 items)
Statesmen--United States--Archival resources.; Civil rights workers--United States--Archival resources.
- University of California, Los Angeles, 1922-1927; 2 boxes
  Scope and Contents
  This series is comprised of exam blue books, class notes, term papers, reports, course notebooks, note cards, and syllabi related to Bunche's course work in law and political science at UCLA. The series also includes the commencement address given by Bunche entitled "The Fourth Dimension of Personality" and his basketball uniform. For letters to Dean C. H. Rieber see Correspondence, series 11.
  Course materials are grouped together according to class (e. g. Commercial Law) where appropriate, and arranged chronologically.
  - Notebook, UCLA classes, circa 1922 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Class notes, Administrative Law, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Notes and midterm quiz.
  - Class notes, Commercial Law, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Class notes and exam blue book, Municipal Administration, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Notebook, Philosophy 3b, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Class notes, Political Science 146, Municipal Government, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Term paper, "The Characteristics and Processes of Roman Law", 1926 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Class notes, Elements of Law, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Exam blue books, Political Science 162, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Term paper, "Human Society and Regulation of Authority", 1926 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Term paper, "Primitive and Modern Legal Systems", 1926 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Class notes, State and Local Administration, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Term paper, "The Nature and Extent of International Law", 1927 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Manuscript, "Marxism and the Negro Question", undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Includes notes.
  - "The Fourth Dimension of Personality," Commencement address and program, 1927
    Includes commencement program, and letter from James Mills.
  - UCLA Basketball uniform, undated (Box 469, Folder 1)
- Harvard Graduate School, 1927-1934; 9 boxes
  This series contains materials related to Bunche's studies of government and political science at Harvard Graduate School. Materials include class notebooks, note cards, course materials and syllabi, master's thesis, dissertation field work from Dahomey and Togoland, bibliography note cards and doctoral dissertation on French colonial administration. Outlines from courses taken at Northwestern University in preparation for dissertation fieldwork are also included. The dissertation is complete, although there is no chapter number 2. (Chapters 1 and 2 were renamed Introduction and Chapter 1 upon submission.)
  Materials are grouped together by course (e.g. Government 23), then arranged in chronological order.
  - Letters of introduction, 1927-1928 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Awards and Scholarships, 1927-1934 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - M.A. course work, Government 19 exam blue book, 1927 November 2 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - M.A. course work, notebooks, Political Theory (1 of 2), 1927 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - M.A. course work, notebooks, Political Theory (2 of 2), 1927 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - M.A. course work, notebooks, Constitutional Law (1 of 2), 1927-1928 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - M.A. course work, notebooks, Constitutional Law (2 of 2), 1927-1928 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - M.A. course work, notebook, English Democratic Ideas, 1927-1928 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    UCLA blue book exams (1925) interleaved within notebook.
  - M.A. course work, exam blue books, Government 4, 1927-1928 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - M.A. course work, notebook, International Law, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - M.A. course work, term papers, International Law, 1927-1928 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - M.A. course work, Municipal Administration syllabus, 1927-1928 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - M.A. course work, notebook, Government 23 (1 of 3), 1927-1928 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - M.A. course work, notebook, Government 23 (2 of 3), 1927-1928 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - M.A. course work, notebook and interfiled notes, Government 23 (3 of 3), 1927-1928 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Master's thesis (1 of 3), 1928 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Master's thesis (2 of 3), 1928 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Master's thesis (3 of 3), 1928 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Ph.D. course work, notebook, Government 21, 1929-1930 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Loose notes interleaved.
  - Ph.D. course work, exam blue books and notebook, Government 24, 1929-1930 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Ph.D. course work, notebook and interfiled notes, Government 24, 1929-1930 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Ph.D. course work, notebook, Public Finance and American History, 1929-1930 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Dissertation and Fellowship application, 1930-1931 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Julius Rosenwald Fund Fellowship, 1931 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Dissertation fieldwork in Africa (1 of 2), 1931-1934 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Dissertation fieldwork in Africa (2 of 2), 1931-1934 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Travel information and maps, Dissertation fieldwork in Africa, 1932-1933 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    Includes travel pamphlets and maps.
  - Letters of recommendation, Dissertation fieldwork, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Dissertation notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Dissertation notes and articles (1 of 2), undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Dissertation notes and articles (2 of 2), undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Notecards, Dahomey and Togoland (1 of 2), undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Dissertation notes.
  - Notecards, Dahomey and Togoland (2 of 2), undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Ph.D. Dissertation, Introduction and Chapter I (i.e., Chapters I and II), 1934 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Ph.D. Dissertation, Chapter III, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Ph.D. Dissertation, Chapter IV, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Ph.D. Dissertation, Chapter V, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Ph.D. Dissertation, Chapter VI, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Ph.D. Dissertation, Chapter VII, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Ph.D. Dissertation, Chapter VIII, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Ph.D. Dissertation, Chapter IX, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Ph.D. Dissertation, Chapter X, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Ph.D. Dissertation, Chapter XI, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Ph.D. Dissertation, Chapter XII and Bibliography, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Ph.D. Dissertation, Appendix, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Ph.D. Dissertation bibliography notecards, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Dissertation bibliography notecards. Includes Library of Congress call slips.
  - "History of Dahomy, an Inland Kingdom of Africa," one volume, 1793 (Box 468, Folder 8)
    Book by Archibald Dalzel. Used by Bunche for Ph.D. dissertation research.
- Howard University, 1928-1952; 6 boxes
  This series is composed of materials related to Bunche's professional teaching and administrative activities during his chairmanship of the political science department at Howard University from 1928 to 1950. Materials include transmittal correspondence arranged by year and faculty memoranda, student recommendations, course materials, lecture notes, and class record books.
  Administrative materials are arranged by type, followed by course materials arranged by course number.
  - Correspondence, 1928-1930 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1931 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1932 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1933 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1935 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1943 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1947-1952 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence and memoranda, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Letter to the editor of the Afro-American, undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Personal recommendations, 1930-1941 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Carnegie Teaching Fellowship in International Law, 1931-1932 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Todd Duncan, 1931-1936 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Thompson-Julian controversy, 1931-1932 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, NYA payroll and time sheets for Howard students, 1935-1936 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Howard University Bulletin, 1940 April 1 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Graduate Council, 1938-1941 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Agenda of questions relative to the revision of the twenty-year plan, 1939 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Faculty memoranda, 1939-1940 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Social Science Division, Joint Committee on National Recovery National Conference, 1935 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Howard University Studies in the Social Sciences publication, 1941 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    "The Negro Federal Government Worker," by Laurence J.W. Hayes.
  - Howard University Conference on Problems of Negro Students, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Student payroll sheets, 1935-1936 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Dean's excuses for Political Science students, 1934-1941 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Schedules of Political Science courses, 1928-1943 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Class record book, 1938-1940 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Class record book, first semester, 1939-1940 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Class record book, second semester, 1939-1940 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Political Science course bibliographies, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Teaching charts, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Exams, lecture notes, course materials, 1930-1938 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Course materials, Constitutional Law, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Course materials, Feudalism and the Feudal State, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Course materials, Government and Labor Workers' Education, undated (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Lecture notes, International Law, undated (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Course materials, Introduction to the Social Sciences, undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Course materials, Pro-seminar in Government Social and Economic Control, undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Course materials, Public Finance, undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Course materials, Modern European History, 1928-1929 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Course materials, American History, 1929-1934 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Course materials, United States Government, undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Course materials, Political Science 1-2, (1 of 3), 1933-1939 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Course materials, Political Science 1-2, (2 of 3), undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Course materials, Political Science 1-2, (3 of 3), undated (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Course materials, Political Science 102, 103, 1935-1941 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Course materials, Political Science 113, undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Course materials, Political Science 126, 1928-1930 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Course materials, Political Science 127, 1929-1937 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Course materials, Political Science 128, 129, 130, 133, 136, 138, 1935-1940 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Course materials, Political Science 133, 1928 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Course materials, Political Science 136, 1929 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Course materials, Political Science 138, undated (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Course materials, Political Science 143, 1931 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Course materials, Political Science 141, 142, 143, 144, 149, 1929-1936 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Course materials, Political Science 147, 1931 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Course materials, Political Science 176, 1931-1938 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Course materials, Political Science 183, 186, 1931-1936 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Course materials, Political Science 191, 1929-1938 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Course materials, Political Science 191, 192, 1935-1941 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Course materials, Political Science 201, 1935 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Course materials, Political Science 202, 203, 204, 205, 206, 1933-1936 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Course materials, Political Science 203, undated (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Course materials, Political Science 204, 1932 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Course materials, Political Science 205, 1931 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Course materials, Political Science 209, 1941 (Box 16, Folder 9)
- Social Science Research Council Fieldwork, 1936-1938; 14 boxes
  In 1936 Bunche received a two year fellowship from the Social Science Research Council for postdoctoral fieldwork and research in Europe and Africa on colonial administration. This series contains research and reference documents by country/area in Africa, clippings, fieldwork notebooks, note cards, photographs, brief correspondence related to the fellowship, a field diary, and letters of introduction.
  Bunche recorded four short films during his fieldwork in Africa and Southeast Asia, which are housed with the Film and Audio Recordings, 1937-1975 series.
  - Correspondence, Social Science Research Council Fellowship, 1937-1938 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    Includes program of study.
  - Correspondence and travel documents, Africa field trip, 1937-1938 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - John Anisfield grant for race relations study, 1939 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Postgraduate Course materials, Anthropology Bibliographies, Northwestern University, 1936-1937 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Postgraduate Course materials, "Psychological types in cultures," Northwestern University paper, circa 1936 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    Includes notes, call slips, and bibliography.
  - Postgraduate Course materials, Economics and Sociology lecture outlines, Northwestern University, circa 1936 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Research documents, East Africa, 1930-1938 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Research documents, Kenya, 1929-1938 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Research documents and correspondence, Kenya, 1932-1937 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Research documents, Kikuyu Central Association (1 of 2), 1937-1938 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    Includes correspondence.
  - Research documents, Kikuyu Central Association (2 of 2), 1930-1938 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Research documents, race relations, 1924-1938 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Research documents, South Africa, 1935 (Box 18, Folder 2)